Hey, Vsauce. Michael here.
Hey đây là Vsauce, tôi là Michael đây.
And I'm in Los Angeles, but today we're going to talk about love.
Tôi đang ở Los Angeles, nhưng hôm nay ta sẽ nói về tình yêu.
You can't buy love, but what if you could? I mean, what if I had a machine that could
Bạn không thể mua chúng, nhưng nếu có thể thì sao? Ý tôi là, nếu có một cái máy
make you fall in love with someone for the rest of your life?
làm bạn say đắm với ai đó cả cuộc đời?
What should I charge for the use of that machine? Well, we should, first of all, be clear about
Tôi nên trả gì để được sử dụng nó? Ta nên trả, trước hết, hãy rõ ràng
what we mean when we say "love." I'm not talking about the love you have for
khi cất lời "yêu". Tôi không nói tình yêu thương giữa
your BFFs or your love for your family or your love of learning.
bạn bè, gia đình hay tình yêu học tập.
I'm also not talking about lust, an immediate attraction we have towards other people mediated
Tôi cũng không nói về thèm khát, một sức hút bất chợt từ người khác là do
by hormones like testosterone and oestrogen. I'm talking about what happens later, when
hóc môn như testosterone và oestrogen. Tôi đang nói về khoảnh khắc sẽ xảy ra lúc sau,
you begin to associate an immediate reward with one other person - what we call passionate
khi bạn bắt đầu hòa mình với cái đáp trả bất chợt từ người khác - thứ ta gọi là tình yêu say đắm.
love. This is what you see in new couples, where
Ta thường thấy ở cặp đôi mới yêu,
they wanna be with each other and are almost obsessed with each other.
họ luôn muốn ở gần nhau và gần như không thể ngừng nghĩ về nhau.
Well psychologists have a really great term for that kind of love.
Những nhà tâm lý học có một thuật ngữ tuyệt vời cho tình yêu như thế.
They call it limerence. That's right.
Họ gọi nó là limerence (trạng thái cảm xúc muốn gắn chặt suy nghĩ, tình cảm, hành vi với một người một cách mãnh liệt và không có chủ đích). Đúng thế đấy.
Whenever you're in this state and you do things like wake up super early to get a bagel with
Mỗi khi trong tình trạng này, bạn làm những điều như thức dậy siêu sớm để thưởng thức bánh mì vòng với nhau
the person and even though you're gonna miss class just because you wanna see them that
dù chuẩn bị trễ học chỉ để gặp người ấy, tệ sao
badly, you're exhibiting limerent behaviour. Okay, that sounds great.
bạn đang bộc lộ hành vi điên tình. Okay, nghe hay đấy.
But if I wanna sell love, I'm gonna have to find a way to measure it and it turns out
Nhưng nếu muốn rao bán tình yêu, tôi phải tìm cách cân đo đong đếm nó, hóa ra
to be quite a difficult task. We do have a tool called the passionate love
ca khó rồi rồi đây. Ta có một thiết bị tên là khảo sát nhiệt ái.
survey. It was developed by psychologists and it's
Được phát triển bởi các nhà tâm lý học
been found to be quite reliable when it comes to analysing other behaviours we associate
nó được chứng tỏ cực kỳ đáng tin khi phân tích hành vi con người trao nhau
with passionate love. For instance, we found, using the survey,
qua tình ái. Ví dụ, ta tìm ra thông qua khảo sát,
that men and women both experience the same amounts of passionate love when they're in
cả đàn ông và phụ nữ đều trải qua một lượng ái tình bằng nhau trong một mối quan hệ.
a relationship. We've also found that men tend to fall in
Ta cũng nhận ra rằng đàn ông thường phải lòng
the love faster and sooner than women, who appear to be more cautious.
nhanh hơn phái nữ, những người thường cẩn trọng hơn.
But we're here to talk about money. Interestingly, a UK study once looked at people
Nhưng ta đang nói về vấn đề tiền nong. Thú vị làm sao, một nghiên cứu tại vương quốc Anh xét đến những người
who heard that someone else loved them. They heard the phrase "I love you" for the
nhận được lời yêu từ một người khác. Lần đầu nghe câu "anh yêu em"
first time and they took the amount of happiness those people felt and compared it to the amount
là họ nhận về một lượng hạnh phúc, bằng cảm nhận và so sánh nó
of happiness gamblers feel when they win large sums of money.
với niềm vui thắng bộn tiền của những con bạc.
Their conclusion, that hearing that someone loves you for the first time is the equivalent
Họ kết luận, lần đầu được nghe tiếng yêu từ ai đó
happiness level of receiving 267,000 dollars. But when you go beyond passionate love to
ta nhận lại lượng hạnh phúc đáng giá tới 267,000 đôla. Nhưng khi đã qua mức ái tình đến
committed long-term love, there's all kinds of practical benefits marriage brings.
tình yêu chính thức bền chặt, hôn nhân mang lại cho đôi bạn những giá trị lợi ích thực tiễn.
In fact, it's been estimated that tax breaks and health care costs all together mean that
Thực tế, người ta ước lượng rằng được giảm chi phí thuế và chăm sóc sức khỏe có ý nghĩa như
being married is the equivalent of receiving an extra 100,000 dollars a year.
kết hôn và nhận thêm một khoản tương đương 100,000 đô một năm.
Now we have a lot of ways of visualizing the effect having money has on a person.
Ngày nay ta có nhiều cách hình dung sức ảnh hưởng của đồng tiền lên người có nó.
For instance, we know that in wealthier countries people report feeling respect more often.
Ví dụ, ta biết ở nước giàu hơn con người thường đưa tin về lòng kính trọng.
They also report eating tastier foods, for instance.
Cả về những loại thức ăn hảo hạng hơn.
But here's what's really awesome. Take a look at the graph of wealth against
Nhưng cái này mới là tuyệt này. Chú ý vào đồ thị biểu diễn mức độ thịnh vượng so với
love.
tình yêu.
It doesn't matter.
Không quan trọng.
Love is democratic, no matter who you are or how much money you have, people all over
Tình yêu là quyền dân chủ, không quan trọng bạn là ai, có bao nhiêu tiền, con người trên khắp thế giới
the world are feeling it. It should be noted that having more money
đều có tình cảm. Cần đính chính một điều rằng không nhất thiết kiếm nhiều tiền hơn
does not necessarily equate to being more happy.
để được hạnh phúc hơn.
This is what's known as the hedonistic treadmill. Getting more money helps with happiness, but
Cái này gọi là vòng xoáy khoái lạc. Kiếm nhiều tiền hơn để hạnh phúc hơn, nhưng chỉ đến một điểm nhất định.
only up to a certain point. In United States that point is about 75,000
Ở Mỹ, điểm này rơi vào khoảng 75000
dollars a year. At that point, more money has diminishing
đô 1 năm. Tại mức này, càng nhiều tiền hơn chỉ làm giảm cảm giác sung sướng
returns on how happy it makes you. Another thing that correlates to having more
của đồng tiền bạn kiếm ra. Tương quan với việc có nhiều tiền hơn,
money, more wealth, is living longer, having a larger life expectancy.
sung túc hơn, là sống lâu hơn, tuổi thọ dài hơn.
But you know what else correlates to living longer?
Nhưng bạn biết thứ gì tương quan để sống thọ hơn không?
Love. But not just passionate love, the kind of
Tình yêu. Nhưng không chỉ ái tình, loại tình yêu theo sau nó,
love that follows it - committed, long-term love.
tình yêu bền chặt, lâu dài.
In fact, people who form life-long pair bonds with another person live, on average, 15%
Thực tế, những người sống cặp lâu dài với bạn đời, trung bình, thọ thêm 15%.
longer. So if you wanna be really non-hard-scienc-y
longer. So if you wanna be really non-hard-scienc-y
about it, all other things being equal and assuming that you're not already super super
about it, all other things being equal and assuming that you're not already super super
rich, finding a pair bond, finding a relationship that lasts for life is the equivalent of making
rich, finding a pair bond, finding a relationship that lasts for life is the equivalent of making
about an extra 30 to 40 thousand dollars a year.
thêm khoảng 30 đến 40 ngàn đôla một năm.
Now, like I said, that's not hard science, but you know what is?
Như tôi đã nói, đó không phải là hard science, nhưng bạn biết gì không?
Vasopressin and oxytocin, the chemicals that are exuded in people's brains when they
Vasopressin và oxytocin, các hóa chất tiết ra trong não người khi họ
look at photos of people that they formed committed, long-term relationships with.
look at photos of people that they formed committed, long-term relationships with.
These chemicals are incredible. We've also seen elevated levels of them in
These chemicals are incredible. We've also seen elevated levels of them in
dogs that have been pet for really long time. And we also know that couples who receive
dogs that have been pet for really long time. And we also know that couples who receive
high levels of these chemicals resolve conflicts faster.
high levels of these chemicals resolve conflicts faster.
And, people who struggle to produce these chemicals in their brain have a similar struggle
And, people who struggle to produce these chemicals in their brain have a similar struggle
when it comes to forming long-term relationships. In fact, you can raise your levels of oxytocin
when it comes to forming long-term relationships. In fact, you can raise your levels of oxytocin
or vasopressin inside your own brain by simply looking into someone else's eyes.
or vasopressin inside your own brain by simply looking into someone else's eyes.
That's right. So, in a way, looking into the eyes of somebody
That's right. So, in a way, looking into the eyes of somebody
that you like is the administration of a psycho-active drug that's addictive and the long-term consequences
that you like is the administration of a psycho-active drug that's addictive and the long-term consequences
are living longer.
are living longer.
Thanks for watching.
Thanks for watching.